so this is a Gina
nakiya hundred and eight
kaulder kopaka Mogollon
in it so it's when venerable ananda who
was living in the squirrel sanctuary not
long after the blessed one had attained
finally bunny the brahmin continues to
ask master nanda master Gautama was
living at Vaishali in the hall the
peaked roof in a great wood then I went
there and approached the master and in
many ways he gave a talk about
meditation hmm Master Dharma was a
meditator cultivated meditation and he
praised every type of meditation every
type of meditation he did he didn't the
best one did not praise every type of
meditation nor did he condemn every type
of meditation so our new meditation he
praised was a meditation John is all
being able to be quite secluded from
central closures when then meditates
yeah meditation is about secluding
yourself from sensual pleasures so
understanding the extent or the sensual
domain the the depth of sense desire and
surmounting it and not just in the sense
of why I don't have any desire right now
so I'm ready to meditate you know
another suit is the Buddha would say a
monk would read review his mind like is
there a sensual desire in me now so no
next question then is well other things
in me now on account of which a future
sensual desire to manifest so you don't
just stop by okay I don't have any
desires I'm fine no okay I don't have
any particular desire but am I still
liable to desire if things change if
something comes along with in my senses
could I not have sin would I guarantee
that I will not have sensual desire
arising in me because I abandon
everything that's a necessary basis for
that sensuality no I'm not sure means
there you go that's your work so
understanding the extent of your sensual
desire genetics and understanding things
on account of which sensual desire
arises so things that you carry here and
now not like when or in the future with
sensual desire arrived
no the Buddha would say before it's
manifested you want to discern things in
your mind better there on account of
which future central desire will be
manifested or what is that that may mean
well the main reason for that is the
lack of context lack of perspective what
is the Buddha said improper I only saw
Manasa car there is not a single thing
they would bring under reason sensual
desire to arise and the reason want to
increase as improper or or that I own is
so monastic are basically loss of
perspective on account of your own
existence situation that's the sole
reason why sensuality would increase or
arise again so what would be the main
lots of perspectives you're paying it to
paying attention to the beautiful design
of the beautiful ism well see that's
already paying it that's that type of
attention it's already the result of you
losing the perspective on a more
fundamental level like I Johnny Samana
see car is not like proper attention
it's not like oh you're attending to
this you focus on certain things and
then everything else gets excluded as we
discussed before Jana Samana seeker is
basically the the the root the origin of
whatever you are attending so if I'm
attending beautiful objects in the world
or if I'm attending ugly objects in the
world Jana saw aspect of that monastic are of
Jana saw aspect of that monastic are of
that attention is my perspective on the
whole situation it's where my attention
is rooted see you would be attending to
the beautiful science for example
because your perspective send you that
way your perspective forgets the danger
of attending to beautiful it forgets the
peril of sensuality and the next thing
you know you're attending to beautiful
science could you forgot you lost the
context exactly so that's what Jana
Samana Saqqara is it's that fundamental
perspective they then directs your
attention this way or that way so that's
why there isn't such a single thing that
could bring sensuality to increase and
no no reason one to arise as
of that perspective on that fundamental
level but see if you never completely
lose perspective on the fact that
sensuality is dangerous no word engaging
in pleasure Annunciation not created if
you develop it even doesn't matter how
many central objects might come your way
that perspective will keep your
attention in check so you will not
attending you will not be attending
carelessly to this aspect they will then
take you to a sensual desire and central
acts and that in itself is already
meditation so when one wants to meditate
that's that's what meditation is
basically developing the strength of
your mind they will take you away from
sensuality not maintain you within it
and then make it grow further and same
with us discuss that a number of talks
people can find me that jhana playlist
it even the first jhana the way it's
described this is we drawn from
sensuality from unwholesome states you
experience joy and pleasure on account
of it all and then your mind is
established in that jhana but somehow
they got perverted in in a course of
time so now people think is okay I'll
just say no temporarily to my desires do
a meditation technique get this special
super refined pleasure pleasurable
experience and that's my jhana as if
like chasing the pleasure of your
focusing is the jhana practice yet the
Buddha said that pleasure that people
chase on a condo jhana
it's actually pleasures of renouncing
the sensuality and then John is the
result of that so jhana follows only
later once you have been withdrawn from
sensuality through and through as it
says in that Sutra knowing the
gratification the escape from it the
your liability or band on the basis that
makes reliable to sensuality to
understand it through discernment
through non losing the context because
you become more and more familiar with
that right perspective then you will
experience joy on account of being
withdrawn fundamentally from that centuries from
fundamentally from that centuries from
central domain in general not this
particular sense desire of that in
general sense desire is a
and that's extremely pleasant and that
pleasure is something that you're
craving cannot fake up because you
haven't done it through your action it's
the result of you be drawing from from
all the pleasures you know pleasures of
sensuality so by being withdrawn from
pleasures of sensuality the side effect
of that is pleasure enunciation which is
what I said you don't have to fear that
pleasure of renunciation because it's
not underlined by craving cannot be
underlined by craving and the same set
for the janitor so that pleasure of
renunciation if you cultivate your mind
then gets established in the first jhana
so first is renunciation understanding
central domain pleasure on account of it
that might take you know a long time to
develop and then you might have to spend
a long time in that pleasure
renunciation and then to discern
thinking and pondering on the level of
the first jhana
so jhana is even a further symptom the
subsequent symptom that comes on account
of you being withdrawn from sensuality
and dwelling as the Buddha would say in
that state whether you go to toilet
extend your arm each stand lay down walk
you'll be abiding in that divine divine
state so if I think I can meditate
before that exactly you will be
meditating within the central domain and
that's a good event you will be
meditating with sensuality and it's not
incidental and not in that suta in
another suit that uses the same
description of meditating with
sensuality but then it also gives the
similes of how would you meditate with
sensuality and each and every simile
basically what it has in common is
focusing practice like like like preying
upon upon a sort of whatever a cat preys
upon a mouse yeah what are you trying to
get something well that's the point
that's the point so if you are not
withdrawn from sensual domain on account
of which you then experience the
pleasure and then jhana develops you
whatever effort you make will be rooted
the central domain in trying to get
pleasure exactly even if you don't necessarily
exactly even if you don't necessarily
think about pleasure in thinking that
you can perform things towards the right
meditation as opposed to understand
things that will make you withdrawn from
them like the whole point of Samadhi is
Rebecca off from unwholesome literally
seclusion from unwholesome states and
you can't do that on account of your
unwholesome states you can only be draw
yourself by undoing basically your lack
of perspective so you are within
unwholesome cause you don't have
perspective on it you start developing
perspective through contemplating
unwholesome the gratification the danger
the escape in regard to desire
that's how not to like or by focusing on
this and after three seconds I do this
and then I move that and then I walk
this step and then the fourth step and
then I do look at this moment and in
that moment and in the next moment
that's you laying out what you're gonna
do fully within on account of your
sensual desires already so even the hope
of practicing the Dhamma is rooted in
sensuality for you because you're going
that way of sensual development so the
Buddha did not go into specifics of like
what you would be doing on a kind of
sensuality he just said unless he abandoned
he just said unless he abandoned
essentially the menu will be meditating
with sensuality how and then it said
like a cat waiting for a mouse like a
bird waiting for a fish
focusing concentrating on one point
where the mouse will show itself and
then I'll pounce then I will get it then
I will grab their jhana and I will have
that supreme pleasure of jhana and I'll
being around and on account of that
you're not you're even further away from
John because you're chasing it as
pleasure failing to see the pleasure is
secondary product of you withdrawal from
sensuality and then the Jannah is
tertiary product of that having
abandoned sensuality he experienced joy
on account of that withdrawal and then
in that state of joyous contentment of
renunciation his mind enters and dwells
abides in that state of John
and saying about you have to understand
what sensuality is the whole you have to
understand there is a third option by
the way you are either not understanding
sensuality which means you are
meditating with it and all your efforts
revolve around it
oh you're making the effort to undo your
wrong views in regards to your own
desires and by by doing so the nature of
those desires will become apparent like
what is the true gratification in the
desire what is the true danger and what
is the true escape that's what that's
the only meditation that were the place
and that we drove up from sensuality is
synonymous for John literally jhana is
the result of your withdrawal from
centrality and again I don't think it
hurts to the emphasize when I say we
draw it doesn't mean like you shut your
door pull your blinds in current you don't
pull your blinds in current you don't
have any desire come in your senses
means internally surmounting with your
mind by understanding for what it is
three people most people have just
driven around by the desires because
they don't have a clue why or how and to
what extent they're controlled by them
so the first thing you need to do is say
no to them and then in do that pain and
then eventually you might be able to
understand the nature of it and that's
what it meant you semantics because
that's what it describes that suit you
carry on like readers what it says when
he says the the Buddha the meditation
that the Buddha did not praise so nots
not having not abandoned the descent of
the scent sensuality still being liable
to sensuality not knowing the escape
from that sensuality he meditates and he
calls himself a meditative and so on and
that's the meditation of it so unless
you have surmounted abandoned understood
you escape from sensuality by the way
not from particular sight sound smell
taste touch the nature of sense desire
the you liable to you're not liable to
anymore that's your right meditation and
that's a necessary condition for Jannah
that's not even jhana yes let's
it's a pre-course it's there's no jhana
without it and practicing that will have
to result in John
it cannot result in anything else so
that's why when the Buddha said in other
sutras in more concise ways when he
would describe what is the right
meditation he would just describe
practice of jhana because it already
implies a thought-out withdrawal from
sense domain that all abandonment of
sensual desire which probably undoes
like 85% of all the wrong views the
people carry are based on their
sensuality nothing else like
sensualities calls like weaken er the
hindrances and centrality weakening of
wisdom but without centrality people
much quicker understand the nature of
things we get the right view built fully
liberated it's the sensuality that keeps you bond
it's the sensuality that keeps you bond
with your own ignorance through your own
choices of finding yourself basically
that sensuality in essence is the
valuing yeah yeah we said that in other
talks it's not like I have this raging
desire or something no no it's way way
more general than that more more
primordial than that it's literally an
attitude of you gratuitously
maintaining value in experience of
pleasure of any kind so you value
pleasure for no reason there is no
reason to value pleasure more than pain
likewise pleasure valuable simply
because it's Pleasant so the pleasure of
the pleasure basically confuses you into
valuing the pleasure as this thing
that's worried to develop to protect to
gain to increase so if you don't value
the pleasure then you would not
basically be subject to that perpetual
desire that is then seeking that
pleasure as the goal and you know again
it can be pleasure of all for sexual
intercourse or food or simply some
lovely peaceful music or or a beautiful
sunset Vista and a cool breeze
if you're seeking that out for the sake
of pleasure on account of your body on
account of your senses its sensual
pleasure if you don't seek it out on
account of that pleasure of your body
then it's just agreeable it's not the
pleasure of sensuality so that's why yes
you can sit on top of a mountain and
admire the view for central reasons or
not for central reasons if you if you
basically have abandoned that gratuitous
value of pleasure being valuable in
itself now certain things certain acts
must stop you cannot possibly do them
without the value of sensuality such as
sexual integrals as the Buddha said
that's impossible to do without already
being within the perception of that
sensual value so engaging in such acts
means you're already implying the value
that you're sure this value of that
pleasure in general now if you go around
leaving your life existing and on the
level of that existence pleasure is the
value for you
you will then be going left and right
seeking things they will provide you
with pleasure because you value it
naturally pleasure is on your mind so
whatever you do is for the sake of
experiencing pleasure because that's you
go why you having that level exactly so
that value that you carry is before you
engage with central sense objects and
that's why you're liable to the desire
toward sense objects because you
actually carry on that lack of
perspective you value pleasure valuing
the pleasure is the result of the lack
of perspective if you have ever
developed perspective on the value of
pleasure you realize that it's
completely not valuable at all doesn't
mean all now I need to experience pain
not at all that's the other extreme just
means I must remove the value of feeling
of pleasure because what is valuable
there's nothing valuable you just assume
that it is and you live your whole life
according to it so feeling is not it's
it comes and goes
it's my mind yep
so if is agreeable food
I recognize it is agreeable but because
I don't have the value of pleasure I
will not have desired for more of that
because it's the more general context of
valuing the pleasure that then
determines how much pleasure you get and
as Inc then creates a discrepancy for
wanting more because the value of
pleasure is on one level and sense
objects and pleasures you get from units
on another and that's why the desire is
insatiable because you're looking
basically for it where it isn't your
desire is that value of pleasure that's
what we would have said that delighting
pleasure as in I delight in the prospect
of experiencing agreeable sense objects
and feelings in general I delight in
that prospect
that's the gratification of my pleasure
everything else is secondary
so you eating the cake or admiring the
Vesta or chasing down relationships or
whatever for the sake of sensual
gratification all that is secondary to
you already gratifying your pleasure by
allowing that value to control you by
maintaining the value of pleasure in
itself and you realize what happens or
what will happen if you stop maintaining
the value of pleasure does that mean you
would go in pain no it doesn't because
if you ask yourself now do a value
pleasure like I'm not engaging with
anything sensual then you could drop
that value loving yourself I don't you
can actually drop the T you can drop
bacon and then you forget about and
that's the point
yeah then you keep reminding yourself
and the more you dwell on it the clearer
it becomes and that's the whole point of
understanding the nature of
understanding is you make the effort to
clarify things that need to be
understood so once that perspective
becomes thoroughly understood you can't
drop it you can't forget about it
in that sense but what I'm trying to say
is that now when people would think oh
if I bend the value of pleasure it's
implicitly assumed oh that means
everything will be painful but it isn't
all you need to do is just ask yourself
now when you are not surrounded by sense
objects you are neither in pain nor in
like you know things are a bit rough in
this jungle but we are used to it so it
doesn't bother us but there are no other
things of agreeable or pleasant nature
inciting either so you ask yourself okay
so in this sort of neutral environment
am I liable to sensuality as in if
things change if things become more
comfortable more agreeable will the
sense desire arising so you're like oh
if you say if you recognize that it will
means okay so I still value experiencing
pleasure at some point sometimes doesn't
matter but you realize that value that
exists right here right now is actually
existing on account of this mutual
feeling you do not engage in pleasure
now that remind you of pleasure that
there you want more pleasure you quite
withdrawn from pleasure now yet somehow
the mind could still value sensuality on
account of which you have the future
sense desire if there is no value of
that pleasure in general future senses
are cannot manifest in you so why don't
you bendin that value right here right
now on account of this neutral feeling
consequently by actually the traders are
maintaining that value of pleasure this
neutral feeling is actually experienced
painfully because you value pleasure
that's your threshold that sugar is
criteria and that's why the Buddha said
when you don't recognize the neutral
feeling that's here it's it's gonna be
felt as unpleasant when you recognize it
it's gonna be felt as pleasant and that
pleasure of neutral feeling is a good
type of Treasury the pleasure you cannot
pray for you see it's not rooted it's
not determined by this value of
sensuality per se so it's just me that
you did you drop the value here now
pleasure hmm I don't want that I don't
need that anymore hmm I don't value it
hasn't given me any lasting anything it
hasn't given me enough anything
then I can resort to depend on and then
you mean you allow that idea to endure
to possess to protect it you cultivate
it you think about it further like see
now you drop it you understand hasn't
also if you have a lemon essential
thoughts come in your mind yeah but I
can remind myself but it's not valuable
so if I realize that yeah I really
realize it the burden off of the value
of getting I must oh yeah the burden
must be burdened drop John and what do
you feel the releases so that release is
that mutual feeling exactly released
into peace which you would have you
always had in front of you but you are
not recognizing and that's the whole
point see when you have a thought say
okay you you do have on some physical
level your restraint and you recognize
I'll never engage with this anymore
you never provides any satisfaction is
just burden further disturbance fine
your establish within that but now in a
more subtler level your mind might have
a thought or something about sensuality
now I must not think that no when that
boat arises include that thought in this
context don't forget the context on
account of the thoughts or not so now I
have these thoughts but this value
remains this sorry the new value of
devalued sensuality remains unchanged so
the loud thoughts to endure central
thoughts if they manifested aloud and
figure against the backdrop of devalued
sensuality so that's how you devalue the
thoughts as well but if you forget about
the perspective and go ahead and deal
with the thoughts and get rid of the
thoughts and oppress the thoughts and
I'll think about it
I will take the hook sure you might not
go physically and engage of sensuality
but you are revolving around it by
fighting the thoughts now you just want
to not lose that right perspective
John is Samana Saqqara even when the
weather is the physical prospect verbal
prospect mental prospect the D values of
sensuality as the new value remains
maintained and protected and the longer
you maintain it and protected the more
of anything like like the discrepancy
calls where central desire will burn
away scorch like the Buddha get what was the
scorch like the Buddha get what was the
simile that the the heat up heated a pen
he throw and instantly the water will
evaporate if it's really really hot
that's your pan the hot pan is a new
value of devalued centrality so doesn't
matter what central object coming your
sight sound smell taste touch thought he
weapon it's instantly because that's you
don't stop it to deal with it you just
maintain the context its values yeah or
another similar of eating the eating the
food and not catching the bait like the
deer so how do you not take the food
that has debate you don't forget about
the bait you don't see the bait but you
know the bait and you get to recognize
where the bait is and you don't eat that
food which means you go around and eat
everything else you want except the one
that would hook you so you can then have
plenty of actions aimed at although I'll
lay down because my back hurts is too
good I would say or oh this is agreeable
Grove let us spend some time here like
you know for protrusion and non free
from sensuality we'll think of what the
Buddha has desires not not the desires
that you think of because when you start
the practice you're fully within
sensuality you don't have a neutral
point from which you can see are a hunt
type of desire and put to general type
of desire you are the pathogen a type of
desire yeah so all you can do is work
your way down from the inside of that
desire and then what you have is not a
desire but yes your intention can still
value avoiding discomfort for example
and it will not be sensual but unless
you are free if you are not free from
sensuality in that fundamental manner as
the Buddha said you don't know the
liability the gratification liability
danger and escape from it then even the
innocent intentions towards agreeable
your dwelling your sleeping place your
food will be thoroughly sensual because
you made it so
so the danger is that value exactly the
danger is not like all see the danger is
if I go out and seek things out and then
things can go not mile the way I wanted
to that's all the result the danger is
implicit before you engage with it in
the same sense gratification is implicit
before you engage with in the same set
the escape is implicit before you engage
gratification is the danger
well the edge is within the
gratification exact gratification is the
aspect of the same thing that's
dangerous recognizing the gratification is the
recognizing the gratification is the
same aspect of the danger is how you get
the escape from it so the just that
value just that happiness that delight
as the Buddha would say on account of
valuing the pleasure
that's the gratification of the pleasure
that's the extent of it now what is the
danger because of that utterly look like
virtually almost abstract value and it's
abstract cause you never stop you know
first you never restraint you know step
back from the sense objects to get
perspective on them and then second you
never think about wait why do I value
pleasure like why do I move from this
comfort into comfort oh let me try
that's why sometimes the Buddha would
say well when today they would ask him
off should you do these ascetic
practices he says well let those who who
know that those practices would bring
the wholesome to increase unwholesome to
decrease let them do it and sometimes
that means let me go in the adverse
enduring of the elements and hardship
because I recognize that as devaluing
automatic devaluing sensuality but it's
not a guarantee you need to know where
the value is and what like oh it's
values gratuitous I must basically
challenge that value internally and that
that does not necessarily mean that
everybody can do the same practice
external in terms of ascetic practices
and and endurance and so on to some
extent yes but - what Xcover you need to
take that that depends on well it
depends on individual but the point is
when you when you recognize that like
literally the danger of that value is
that you have this value of pleasure
from the level of like Oh pleasure of
satisfying your curiosity
to the level of pleasure of you know the
wildest unrestrained music drugs alcohol
sexual intercourse the whole thing it's
all within the same domain of I value
pleasure so you realize because you choose to
so you realize because you choose to
value pleasure
you make yourself liable you seek it out
over there in this wild world that
you're not in control like people I mean
people work like you know their hands to
the bone just so they can earn just so
they can provide themselves with
pleasure though the family children
spouses the whole thing it's all under
the value of I just want pleasure now I
can be moderate about it I can be
restrained to some extent but I cannot
be so but fundamentally either way I
still value pleasure because of that I
am liable literally to the danger of
this very dangerous world I have
confidence in a place you could see you
would not suffer if things fall and
break and snap your arm in half like it
would be uncomfortable but you will not
have mental despair and fear on account
of that happening to you if you don't
have any desire toward using their arm
for pleasure but you have already see
the implicit is implicit value of
pleasure on that mental level creates
the value of the body as your tool
toward the pleasure so if something
helps to that the body that prevents you
from gaining the pleasure later on lads
then the price of real pain and that's a
good asset
what is dukkha not getting what you want
is dukkha and getting what you don't
want is Duke
so having desired towards this not
having that is dukkha and having desire
against this and having that is dukkha
so you can't get rid of things when you
want this data and you can't get things
when you want is dukkha like experiences
are always dukkha because of that
central value
yes so you're liable to this massive
suffering indirectly so to speak like
your value of sensuality is mental
existential so to speak your value of
pleasure on account of it you go along
with a society with what people do with
the values and family and work and
earning all of that all of that is
within the big domain the big bubble of
valuing pleasure comfort security all of
it all of it all of it and that is very
very uncertain and you know it's
uncertain when you lose the perspective
of on that uncertainty because you value
pleasure valuing pleasure for gratuitous
reason makes you fundamentally
irrational yeah it's called removing just that you
yeah it's called removing just that you
don't need to destroy the world you just
need to remove your value of the
pleasure in regard to the world and then
nothing can affect you you lose your
life you lose your health well because
there was no end game to it
but with a value of pleasure that is
always an end game of more pleasure so
there is no nothing for you to suffer on
account of because you don't value
pleasure which means you don't
automatically devalue pain you don't
automatically fear the prospect of pain
you're indifferent towards it
[Music]
and yeah like in modern world comfort is
one of the kind of I mean most people
don't even see how much they depending
on which areas extent amounts of comfort
like soft beds and doers and tillers and
and carpets and socks in and just just
comfort comfort comfort comfort comfort
and you wouldn't even necessarily think
of that as sensuality yet it's fully
completely within the value why'd you
value comfort or because you value
pleasure ology why do you become
irrationally terrified anxious at the
prospect of sense restraint and the
prospect of physical discomfort for a
period of time you know like when you
like when people you see the like when
they go hiking or something and after
like half an hour of just fatigue sets
in how cranky they become and an
irritable just because nothing is like
really bothered you are affected you you
know you're not even either greater a
pain but you just lost the threshold of
the comfort you used to because you
you're getting something which you do
not value at all and that's which is not
enough pleasure well yeah exactly that's
I mean it pushes you you create ya you
create this gaping hole that can never
be fulfilled by valuing that pleasure in
the mental level but the only way you
can seek it out is on the level of your
senses if you don't value pleasure when
it's there it's nothing solid well there
is no discrepancy that you need to
fulfill if you don't value pleasure
that's not there means whatever's there
is fine in itself so in the scene there
will just be the scene in the herd they
will just be the herd and so on you can
literally then continue with the same
principle and say in the felt there will
be just the felt in the perceive there
will be just the perceived there'll be
no more misconceiving towards are the
future the future kind of implications
and desires that are rooted in you
literally holding on to the value of
pleasant that's it
and that's when that Suton woulda gave
the simulators Lee Chavez wasn't it they
were sleeping on the hard bed with
wooden blocks as pillows and for as long
as they do that nor the kingdom can
conquer them but the future in the
future the time will come when they will
go soft they will they will they will
have soft soft foot where they will
sleep on soft weddings have soft pillows
they will become fair with soft feet and
hand skin get up after the Sun comes up
yeah yeah lazy and getting up and then
they'll be overwhelmed by the kingdom no
bruh and then he said he gave the same
comparison to the monk monk who does who
sleeps one of wooden pillow on a hard
surface Maura will have much harder time finding
Maura will have much harder time finding
access in him a monk who wears very
comfortable robes lives in a comfortable
environment with abundance and food
abundance of comfort abundance of
mattresses abundance of pillows
abundance of heat abundance of Drive
where their abundance of very very nice
things that are not central or layman's
terms they're just comfortable you know
sleeping on a pillow is not like a
raging sensuality yet because of that
you are liable to Iranian society
because the comfort is just a subtle way
as I said even the the pleasure of
curiosity unless you abandon the value
of sensual or that of of pleasant on the
level of mind even that sensual how much
more in the domain yeah it's fully
within the dimensional Shalit
they said you pray to alive Bible you're
in its feeding grounds so then if the
monks that does expose himself to
discomfort not you know you don't need
to be stabbing yourself and cutting
yourself and torturing yourself just
don't make the nests all the excess
effort towards the comfort and then
you'll be fine so valuing pleasure again
is the entry point into the being hunted
by century in a way it's but not entry
point as if you were outside and then
somehow you make a choice you are
already within it so
valuing the pleasure is is is a
framework that it's basically your
existence is already within the plan
your pleasure that's why the Kama Baba
the being of sensuality and that's what
is so difficult to give up exactly it's
not a part your intentions are already
the result of that of that value of that
lack of perspective your choices so you
need to kind of undo it from the inside
while you're affected by it you need to
find a way out of it but it is possible
if you start looking in the right things
things to the Billa tell you should look
at or what what will be the same for
last hours so the point is you reckon as
you value pleasure and that is the
framework for any experience of pleasant
or unpleasant which means through that
framework pleasure will be create form
or through that framework pain will be
created for less through that framework
neutral feeling will be basically
ignored and through if you abandon that
framework neutral feeling will not be
more than will be pleasant and you will
not be trying to get rid of the pain and
you will not seek the pleasure
so then pleasure will arise in pleasant
they will just be the pleasant and
unpleasant they will just be
unpleasantly neutrally we just be
neutral there is no seeking trying to get away
there is no seeking trying to get away
the discrepancy of seeking see seeking
is all the discrepancy what you have and
what you seek that's created by the that
perpetual maintenance feeding off the
current present here and now value of
pleasure and that's what we were meant
Oh other things in me right here right
now on account of which future sense and
desire can manifest as in is this
framework still maintained by me and am
I still valuing the pleasure however
implicitly and if you if you see it that
by seeing it you can actually abandon it
oh let me devalue it because it's not
valuable let me regard it just for the amusement
let me regard it just for the amusement
sake the value of pleasure let me
regarded as dangerous perilous painful
resulting in charnel grounds being
filled and then guess what it is that
and because you've been valuing it how
it actually is you get to see it for
what it actually is so initially you
took it on faith that value of pleasant
is very very dangerous but if you start
applying it you get to see it because it
actually facts
is so very dangerous if it were solved
the buddha would have said oh you should
abandon it for your own welfare